1945. My dearest one, I have just heard the news that all the army men taken POW are to
return to their homes. Because of the shipping situation, we may not commence to go before
the end of February, but can probably count on being in England sometime in March. Maybe
sooner. It has made me very warm inside. It's terrific. It's wonderful. Shattering.
I don't know.
what to say and I cannot think. The delay is nothing. The decision is everything. Now
I am confirming in my head the little decisions I have made when contemplating just the possibility.
I must spend the first days at home. I must see Deb and her mother. I must consider giving
a party somewhere. Above all, I must be with you. I must warm you, surround you, love you
and be kind to you. Tell me anything that's in your mind.
mind, write tons and tons and tons and plan our time. I would prefer not to get
married, but want you to agree on the point.
In the battle I was afraid for you, for my mother, for myself. Wait, we must, my
love, my darling.
Let us meet, let us be, let us know, but do not let us now make any mistakes.
I am anxious, very anxious, that you should not misunderstand what I have said.
Say what you think, but please agree and remember I was afraid and I am still afraid.
How good for us to see each other before I am completely bald!
Have a few fine wisps of hair on the top of my head.
Not much good me trying to write about recent experiences now that I know I shall be able
to tell you everything myself within such a short time.
What I have my eye on now is the first letter from you saying that you know I am alright
and then next saying you know I am coming to you.
Must try and keep out of hospital with some of these post-POW complaints.
Plan a week somewhere, not Boscombe or Bournemouth, and think of being together.
The glory of you.
When I was captive I used to try and...
and contact you and think hard.
Bessie, my dearest, I'm all right.
Do not worry.
I never thought that I would get through somehow,
but now it's over and you know that I'm all right
and gonna be with you soon to join and enjoy.
Do not get very excited outwardly.
I am conscious of the inner tumult, the clamor,
but I am not too much outwardly joyful.
Moderation is my advice.
Watch the buses as you cross the streets.
Disinational.
We're free of duties and yesterday I went to our friends in Athens taking some of your
coffee and cocoa which they were very pleased to have. Thank you for sending it. We were
embraced very excitedly kissing and so on, continental fashion.
I hope that you will not start buying any clothes if you have any coupons left because
you think you must look nice for me. I shall be sorry if you do. Just carry on.
on as near as possible to normal. My return at the present time allows us to make public
our mutual attachment. I shall tell my family that I hope to spend a week away with you
somewhere during my leave. My counsel to you is to tell as few people as possible. To someone
like Miss Ferguson, you can politely reply to observations that you thought it was your
business rather than hers. Try to avoid preening yourself and saying much. This is my advice
to you.
Thank you.
Not anything but that.
I hope you understand.
I do not ever want it to be anything but our affair.
Do not permit any intrusion.
I do not know how long leave I shall get.
I could get as little as 14 days
and I may get as much as a month.
I'm wondering how I shall tell you that I am in England.
Probably it would still be quicker
to send a telegram than a letter
and I hope to send you one,
announcing that.
I am on the same island. I will send another when I'm actually soon to get on the London-bound
train and you can ring Lee Green 0509 when you think I have arrived there.
You must bear in mind that I shall be with my brother until we get home. Also, that having
been away from home for so long, my parents will want to see a lot of me.
I hope that everything will work itself out without any unhappiness to anyone. I shall
be in great demand from two or three points and it will be difficult to manage without
offence.
Strange thing, but I cannot seem to get going and write very freely. All I'm thinking about
is I am going home, I'm going to see her. It's a fact, a real thing, an impending event
like Trove Tuesday, Christmas Day, or the Lord Mayor's Banquet. You have to be abroad,
you have to be really, truly...
Permetically sealed off from your intimates,
from your home to realize what a gift this going home is.
The few letters of yours that I had on me,
I burnt the day previous to our surrender,
so no one but myself has read your words.
In the first 10 days of our captivity,
I did not think any soft thoughts about you.
All I did was concentrate on trying to tell you
I was all right.
But when we had a few supplies dropped by aircraft...
great risk to themselves in the misty snow-bound Greek mountain villages, and we started hoping
we might get sent home upon our release. I was always wondering about you, about us.
It is a pity that the winter weather will not be kind to us out of doors, but it would
be nice sitting next to you in the pictures, no matter what may be on the screen. It would
be grand to know that we have each other's support and sympathy.
Wouldn't it be wonderful to be together, really together.
in the flesh, not just to know that the letter is all we can send.
I love you, Chris.